A Finding Aid to the Esther McCoy Papers, circa 1876-1990, bulk 1938-1989, in the Archives of American Art AAA.mccoesth
Archives of American Art
- Correspondence, 1896-1989; Series 2; (Boxes 1-6, 4.9 linear feet)
  - General Correspondence, 1922-1989; 2.3
    - General Correspondence, 1953-1959 (Box 4, Folder 43-46)
    - General Correspondence, 1960-1965 (Box 4, Folder 47-51)
    - General Correspondence, 1966-1968 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
    - General Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 5, Folder 5-8)
    - General Correspondence, 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 9-13)
    - General Correspondence, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 14-16)
    - General Correspondence, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 17-19)
    - General Correspondence, 1976-1978 (Box 5, Folder 20-24)
    - General Correspondence, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 25-27)
    - General Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 28-32)
    - General Correspondence, 1982-1983 (Box 5, Folder 33-37)
    - General Correspondence, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 38-41)
    - General Correspondence, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 42-44)
    - General Correspondence, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 45-47)
    - General Correspondence, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 1-4)
    - General Correspondence, 1988 (Box 6, Folder 5-7)
    - General Correspondence, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 8-10)
    - Undated Correspondence, A-Z, circa 1940s-1980s (Box 6, Folder 11-14)
    - Undated and Unidentified Correspondence, circa 1940s-1980s (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Personal Writings, 1919-1989; Series 3; (Boxes 6-14; 8.1 linear ft.)
  This series contains writings not directly relating to McCoy's career as an architectural historian and critic. Included are scattered diaries, drafts of her personal memoirs, and numerous notebooks. Also found are drafts of published and unpublished works of fiction written by McCoy, and writings by McCoy's friends and colleagues.
  The series is organized into five subseries:
  3.1: Diaries, 1919-1972
  3.2: Notebooks, circa 1930s-1983
  3.3: Memoirs, circa 1940s-1989
  3.4: Fiction, circa 1929-1988
  3.5: Writings by Others, circa 1920s-1989, undated
  - Diaries, 1919-1972; 3.1
    This series contains six diaries belonging to Esther McCoy as well as two travel diaries belonging to her mother, Katie Mae McCoy. Esther McCoy's "Sophomore Days" volumes contain journal entries and mementos from her 1919 school year. Two diaries document her time at Central College for Women (1920) and Baker University (1922-1924), and a diary from 1926 records her first year in New York City. Also found is a personal journal documenting her 1972 trip to Europe.
    - Diary, "Sophomore Days, Volume 1,", 1919 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Diary, "Sophomore Days, Book 3,", 1919 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Diary, early 1920s (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Diary, 1922-1924 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Diary, 1926 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - "Journal: 1972 Trip to London, Paris, Vienna, Venice, Milan," (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - "Diary of European Tour," Katie Mae McCoy, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - "Diary of Alaskan Trip," Katie Mae McCoy, 1957 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Notebooks, circa 1930s-1983; 3.2
    Found here are notebooks kept by McCoy throughout her professional career. The notebooks consist of travel itineraries, travel notes, notes about architecture and folk art seen during trips, notes on interviews with architects, notes about architects and buildings, notes for articles, and other miscellaneous jottings and writings. The notebooks are difficult to decipher, as most were handwritten in pencil.
    Because many notebooks are not dated and do not appear to have subject headings, they are arranged in rough chronological order.
    - Notebook, circa 1930s (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Notebooks, circa 1940s (Box 6, Folder 25-26)
    - Notebooks, 1950-1954 (Box 6, Folder 27-30)
    - Notebooks, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 31-35)
    - Notebooks, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 36-37)
    - Notebooks, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 1-3)
    - Notebooks, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 4-7)
    - Notebooks, 1958-1959 (Box 7, Folder 8-12)
    - Notebooks, circa 1950s (Box 7, Folder 13-36)
    - Notebooks, 1960-1962 (Box 8, Folder 1-5)
    - Notebooks, 1963-1969 (Box 8, Folder 6-10)
    - Notebooks, circa 1960s (Box 8, Folder 11-23)
    - Notebooks, 1970-1972 (Box 8, Folder 24-28)
    - Notebooks, 1973-1974 (Box 8, Folder 29-32)
    - Notebooks, 1975-1976 (Box 8, Folder 33-34)
    - Notebooks, 1976-1983 (Box 9, Folder 1-4)
    - Notebooks, circa 1970s (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Loose Pages from Notebooks, circa 1940s-1950s (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Memoirs, circa 1940s-1989; 3.3
    This series contains autobiographical writings by Esther McCoy documenting various moments in her life. Many of these writings are in a short story format and were given a title by McCoy. Subjects covered in her memoirs, some of which were published, include her mother, childhood, and living in New York and Malibu. Also of note is the piece of writing titled "Geoff/Bo: Paris" describing her time in Paris in 1928 and her relationship with Geoffrey Eaton, and the story "Happy Birthday RMS" about working for architect R. M. Schindler. A folder of manuscripts about Theodore Dreiser contains drafts of three manuscripts relating to Helen and Theodore Dreiser and other literary figures McCoy knew in New York during the 1920s and 1930s. One titled manuscript about Dreiser, "Outward Journey" (1946-1947), can also be found in this subseries.
    Folders are arranged in alphabetical order.
    - [About Her Mother], circa 1960s (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - [Abraham Christopher Columbus III], circa 1960s (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - [Annie the Dog], circa 1970s (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - "Auction at Four-Ten" ("Daga at Four-Ten"), circa 1950s (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - "The Dream,", circa 1975 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - "Driving in England,", circa 1950s (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - "Family Eating: 1919" and "Family Reading: 1919,", 1958 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - "Geoff/Bo: Paris,", circa 1950s (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - "Happy Birthday RMS,", circa 1950 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - [Malibu in the 1930s], circa 1960s (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - "My Life in the Arts,", cira 1963 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - "My Summer in the Museum of Modern Art,", 1946-1947 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - [New York in the 1920s], circa 1950s (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - "Outward Journey,", 1946-1947 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - "A Pail of Roasting Ears,", 1955 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - "Patchin Place,", circa 1950s (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - "Reading," ("How to Read"), circa 1940s (Box 9, Folder 23)
    - "Robert Venturi: To Whom it May Concern,", 1987-1988 (Box 9, Folder 24)
    - "Story of Jean,", circa 1950s (Box 9, Folder 25)
    - [Theodore Dreiser,], circa 1960s-1989 (Box 9, Folder 26)
    - Loose Notes on 1974 Presidential Impeachment (Box 9, Folder 27)
    - Notes and Fragments Writings for Memoirs, circa 1950-1960s, 1979 (Box 9, Folder 28)
  - Fiction, circa 1929-1988; 3.4
    Fictional works found in this subseries include drafts of novels, short stories, and teleplays written by McCoy. A folder of stories submitted to H.L. Mencken includes introductions endorsing the stories by Theodore Dreiser and Edgar Lee Masters with related correspondence. Many of the short stories in this subseries were published in literary magazines and journals, and files may contain correspondence regarding publication and related notes. Of note is a series of files for McCoy's short story, The Pepper Tree, which includes related writings and research material about Japanese internment camps during World War II.
    The life of a California architect forms the basis for drafts of three novels, L.A. L.A., The Vickery Job, and Ward and Associates. These three sets of draft manuscripts appear to be closely connected, although it is not clear if they were stages in the development of a single novel. Other draft novels found here include Land Gerard, June is the Cruelest Month, and The Wind's Eye. None of these novels were published.
    Works of Fiction are arranged by title. In some cases McCoy used more than one title for a developing story, and alternative titles are provided in parentheses. Numbers were assigned to drafts to facilitate research and do not necessarily indicate that the drafts were written sequentially according to the numbers. Though an effort has been made to ensure that related papers are filed together, most of the drafts are undated, and it is impossible to be sure when, and in what order, they were written. Date spans for folders may indicate the date writing began and/or the date of publication and sale. Where possible, these dates have been taken from notations on the manuscripts or from information provided on publication lists.
    - Records of Published and Unpublished Writings (incomplete), circa 1940s-1950s (Box 9, Folder 29)
    - Stories Submitted to H.L. Mencken, 1943 (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - 7 O'Clock Train from Rome, circa 1957 (Box 9, Folder 31)
    - 1849: New York City, circa 1940s (Box 9, Folder 32)
    - The Adoption, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - And Devoutly Kneeling, circa 1940s (Box 9, Folder 34)
    - Anna's Eye ( Mourning Bride), circa 1940s (Box 9, Folder 35-36)
    - The Bearer and the Borne, 1946 (Box 9, Folder 37)
    - Bifel In That Season ( In That Season On That Day), circa 1950s (Box 9, Folder 38)
    - The Big Project, circa 1960 (Box 9, Folder 39)
    - Big Town, circa 1950s (Box 9, Folder 40)
    - Blackberry Winter, 1930 (Box 9, Folder 41)
    - The Blindness of Mrs. Moore, circa 1950 (Box 9, Folder 42)
    - Blonde Bomber ( The Impossible Takes Longer), circa 1942 (Box 9, Folder 43)
    - The Blue Rug, 1962 (Box 9, Folder 44)
    - The Bonzai Tree ( The Earthward Tree), 1960 (Box 9, Folder 45-46)
    - The Boy Lost Forever ( Beefy Brenda), circa 1950s (Box 9, Folder 47)
    - [Brasilia] (Fragments), circa 1959-1961 (Box 9, Folder 48)
    - But Not Love, 1938 (Box 9, Folder 49)
    - The Candy Kid, circa 1950s (Box 9, Folder 50)
    - The Cape, 1946-1949 (Box 9, Folder 51)
    - Cause of Death ( The Window), circa 1950s (Box 9, Folder 52)
    - The Character of Lucy Barr, 1948 (Box 9, Folder 53)
    - A Circuit Rider's Wife, circa 1940s (Box 9, Folder 54)
    - The Client, circa 1955 (Box 9, Folder 55)
    - The Coffee is All Right ( The Clinic), circa 1950s (Box 9, Folder 56)
    - Cover Shot, circa 1940s (Box 9, Folder 57)
    - Dance of Death, 1942 (Box 9, Folder 58)
    - The Day of the Twenty-Third Confession, circa 1950 (Box 9, Folder 59)
    - The Day the Picassos Were Gone, circa 1940s (Box 9, Folder 60)
    - Dear Jim, circa 1940s (Box 9, Folder 61)
    - Divorce in Cuernavaca, circa 1950s (Box 9, Folder 62)
    - A Dog Poisoner, 1953 (Box 9, Folder 63)
    - Don't Make Me Cry, circa 1940s (Box 9, Folder 64)
    - Duffy, Manuel, and the Aquaduct, circa 1940s (Box 9, Folder 65)
    - The Dummy, circa 1940s (Box 9, Folder 66)
    - Emergency, circa 1959 (Box 9, Folder 67)
    - Fairy Story, circa 1929 (Box 9, Folder 68)
    - The Family Plot, 1949-1951 (Box 9, Folder 69)
    - Family Style: Circa 1920, circa 1950s (Box 9, Folder 70)
    - The Featherbed Rut, 1961-1962 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
    - Fire Bug, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - The Fire in the Moon, circa 1959 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - The Giver and the Gift, circa 1960 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Goodtime Charley, circa 1946 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - The Hidden One, 1946-1952 (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - High Heels, 1948-1950 (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - High Street, circa 1940s (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - The House, circa 1950s (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - The House That Refused to Die, circa 1950s (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - I Am Roger, circa 1955 (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - I Call to Simon, circa 1950s (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - If You Wait Long Enough, 1936 (Box 10, Folder 14)
    - The Important House, 1948, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 15)
    - Is She a Teenage Mother?, circa 1968 (Box 10, Folder 16)
    - June is the Cruelest Month, Draft 1, circa 1988 (Box 10, Folder 17-18)
    - June is the Cruelest Month, Draft 2, circa 1988 (Box 10, Folder 19)
    - June is the Cruelest Month, Draft 3, circa 1988 (Box 10, Folder 20-21)
    - June is the Cruelest Month, Draft 4, circa 1988 (Box 10, Folder 22-24)
    - June is the Cruelest Month, Draft 5, circa 1988 (Box 10, Folder 25-26)
    - June is the Cruelest Month, Draft Fragments and Notes, circa 1988 (Box 10, Folder 27-29)
    - The Lady from the Sea, circa 1947 (Box 10, Folder 30)
    - LA, LA, Draft 1, circa 1960s (Box 10, Folder 31)
    - LA, LA, Draft 2, circa 1960s (Box 10, Folder 32)
    - LA, LA, Draft 3, circa 1968 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - LA, LA, Draft 4, circa 1960s (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
    - LA, LA, Draft 5, 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - LA, LA, Draft Fragments, circa 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - LA, LA, Notes and Printed Material, circa 1950-1968 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Land Gerard, Draft 1, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Land Gerard, Draft 2, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 11, Folder 8-11)
    - Land Gerard, Draft 3, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Land Gerard, Draft 4, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 11, Folder 13-15)
    - Land Gerard, Draft 5, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 11, Folder 16-18)
    - Land Gerard, Draft Fragments, circa 1940s-1960s (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Leo Gallagher, circa 1940s (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Lily Bird, 1941-1946 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Limbo, 1938 (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - Listen Caroline, 1942 (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - Lost Sister, circa 1950s (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - Luke, 1943-1945 (Box 11, Folder 25)
    - Main Street, Heaventown, circa 1940s (Box 11, Folder 26)
    - The Male Grapes, 1946-1947 (Box 11, Folder 27)
    - The Man Who Dreamed of Murder ( Suspense), circa 1940s (Box 11, Folder 28)
    - The Man Who Remembered Everything, 1958 (Box 11, Folder 29)
    - The Man With the Birthmark, circa 1953 (Box 11, Folder 30)
    - Miss Vanity Fair, circa 1940s (Box 11, Folder 31)
    - The Mortgage, circa 1951 (Box 11, Folder 32)
    - Mother Lies in the Baggage Coach, 1943-1945 (Box 11, Folder 33)
    - Murder at the Oleanders, circa 1940s (Box 11, Folder 34)
    - Murder to Music, circa 1940s (Box 11, Folder 35)
    - The New Terrain, 1954-1957 (Box 11, Folder 36)
    - The Old House, circa 1940s (Box 11, Folder 37)
    - One and Divisible, 1943-1947, 1958 (Box 11, Folder 38)
    - People Never Learn, 1936 (Box 11, Folder 39)
    - The Pepper Tree, Drafts, circa 1941-1948 (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
    - The Pepper Tree, Notes and Related Writings, circa 1940s (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - The Pepper Tree, Research Material, 1941-1947 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - The Pepper Tree, Published Copies, 1953 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - The Pickpocket Murder, circa 1948 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - A Poem About War Ending, 1946-1947 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Poetry, circa 1970-1985 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - The Print, circa 1943 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - The Quarrel ( The Summer House), 1950-1951 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - The Quiet Season ( The Woman Who Was Trained), 1948-1951 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Remind God, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Return, 1945 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Robin's Sister, 1945-1950 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - The Sin of Puppchen Graff, 1947 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - The Snapshot, 1947 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Solitaire, 1932 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - The Special Delivery Letter, 1954-1956 (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Stay With Me Flagons, circa 1940s (Box 12, Folder 20)
    - St. Bernard, circa 1940s (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - St. Stephen, 1943 (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Suicide Clinic, circa 1940s (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - The Sweet Gum Tree, circa 1946 (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - The Sweet River Trip, circa 1950s (Box 12, Folder 25)
    - Tell Me, Tell Me, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 26)
    - There's No Place To Run, circa 1950s (Box 12, Folder 27)
    - They Designed it Themselves, 1951 (Box 12, Folder 28)
    - Tomorrow's Soldier, circa 1950s (Box 12, Folder 29)
    - Trouble With Phillip ( The Lightening Holes), 1944-1951 (Box 12, Folder 30)
    - The Try-Out ( The Summer House), 1962 (Box 12, Folder 31)
    - Two Dollar Job, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 32)
    - Uncle Haz and the Leafage, 1946 (Box 12, Folder 33)
    - Uncle Walt and the Dalton Boys, circa 1950 (Box 12, Folder 34)
    - The U. S. Marshalls Mrs. Bounds Knew (See Also Uncle Walt and the Dalton Boys), 1937 (Box 12, Folder 35)
    - Valentine's II Less Six, circa 1947 (Box 12, Folder 36)
    - The Vickery Job, Draft 1, Book 1, circa 1970s (Box 12, Folder 37)
    - The Vickery Job, Draft 2, Book 1, circa 1970s (Box 12, Folder 38)
    - The Vickery Job, Draft 2, Book 2, circa 1970s (Box 12, Folder 39)
    - The Vickery Job, Draft 3, circa 1970s (Box 12, Folder 40)
    - The Vickery Job, Draft 4, Book 3, circa 1970s (Box 12, Folder 41)
    - The Vickery Job, Draft 5, Book 1, circa 1970s (Box 12, Folder 42)
    - The Vickery Job, Draft 5, Book 2, circa 1970s (Box 12, Folder 43)
    - The Vickery Job, Draft 6, Book 1, circa 1970s (Box 12, Folder 44)
    - The Vickery Job, Draft 6, Book 2, circa 1970s (Box 12, Folder 45)
    - The Vickery Job, Draft Fragments, circa 1970s (Box 12, Folder 46)
    - The Vickery Job, Notes, circa 1968-1977 (Box 12, Folder 47)
    - The Voices, 1944-1951 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Ward and Associates, Draft 1, circa 1960s (Box 13, Folder 2-4)
    - Ward and Associates, Draft 2, circa 1960s (Box 13, Folder 5-6)
    - Ward and Associates, Draft 3, circa 1960s (Box 13, Folder 7-8)
    - Ward and Associates, Draft 4, circa 1960s (Box 13, Folder 9-11)
    - Ward and Associates, Draft Fragments, circa 1960s (Box 13, Folder 12-16)
    - Ward and Associates, Outlines and Notes, circa 1960s (Box 13, Folder 17-19)
    - Ward and Associates, Source Material, circa 1963-1969 (Box 13, Folder 20)
    - When Writing Mention This Number, circa 1950 (Box 13, Folder 21)
    - The Wind's Eye, Draft 1, circa 1949 (Box 13, Folder 22)
    - The Wind's Eye, Draft 2, circa 1949 (Box 13, Folder 23-24)
    - The Wind's Eye, Draft 3, Part 1, circa 1949 (Box 13, Folder 25)
    - The Wind's Eye, Draft 3, Part 2, circa 1949 (Box 13, Folder 26)
    - The Wind's Eye, Draft 3, Part 3, circa 1949 (Box 13, Folder 27)
    - The Wind's Eye, Draft 4, Part 2, circa 1949 (Box 13, Folder 28)
    - Work for the Night is Coming, 1943-1944 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Untitled Writings, Fragments, and Notes, circa 1940s-1970s (Box 14, Folder 2-3)
  - Writing by Others, circa 1920s-1989, undated; 3.5
    This series contains writings, some in draft form, by McCoy's friends and colleagues. Included are several pieces of writing about architecture, urban planning, and design. Of note are two essays about Esther McCoy written by architect Denise Scott Brown, and writings by architects Evans Woollen, Yona Friedman, and Paul Sterling Hoag. Also found are short stories written by McCoy's lovers, John Mitchell and Albert Robert, including a story by Albert Robert as "Pierre St. Clement," and unidentified writings not written by McCoy.
    This subseries has been partially scanned.
    Files are arranged alphabetically by author.
    - Denise Scott Brown, "Knowing Esther McCoy" and "Esther McCoy and The Second Generation,", 1988-1989 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - J. K. Cruz, "Pressure at Their Respective Crises Zones" ("The Variances"), circa 1970s (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Jean Evans, "Three Studies in Conflict,", circa 1952 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Jean Evans, "The Golden Years (Introduction),", undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Yona Friedman, "A Research Program for a Scientific Method of Planning,", undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Cecil Gray, "Chameleon's Dish,", undated (Box 14, Folder 9)
    - Paul Sterling Hoag, "Wisdom From the Doheny's Back Hall,", 1987 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - Raymond Marcel, "Builders and Humanists: The Renaissance Popes as Patrons of the Arts,", 1966 (Box 14, Folder 11-13)
    - Gabriel Garcia Maroto, "Popular Architecture in Mexico,", undated (Box 14, Folder 14)
    - Mrs. J. L. McCoy, "A Fictionalized Story of the Book of Philemon,", undated (Box 14, Folder 15)
    - John Mitchell, Various Writings, circa 1920s-1930s (Box 14, Folder 16-18)
    - Paul B. Ohannesian, "Letters from Pauline Schindler: 1969-1977,", circa 1977 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    - Albert Eide Parr, "Paths of Dispersal and Encounter in the City,", circa 1970 (Box 14, Folder 20)
    - Albert Robert, "Temporary Gentlemen,", circa 1930s (Box 14, Folder 21)
    - Stephen Spender, "I Think Continually?,", 1934 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    - Pierre St. Clement (Albert Robert), "Heroism and Other Magic,", circa 1930s (Box 14, Folder 23)
    - Eleanor Walker, "The Nineteen Forty-Niners of Malibu Hills,", circa 1949 (Box 14, Folder 24)
    - Evans Woollen, "Towards an Architecture of Process,", 1984 (Box 14, Folder 25)
    - Various Authors, Department of Architecture, National Institute of Fine Arts, Mexico, Conference Presentations, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 26)
    - Unidentified Authors, Miscellaneous Writings, 1949, 1971, undated (Box 14, Folder 27)
- Architectural Writings, 1908-1990; Series 4; (Boxes 14-24, 42, 49, 50; 10.2 linear feet)
  McCoy published numerous articles, essays, books, and exhibition catalogs about modern architecture. She also lectured extensively on this subject. This subseries contains records of her research for, and publication of, these writings and lectures. Found here is correspondence relating to her research; drafts; financial records; printed material including publicity for, and reviews of, her work; research material; and related photographs.
  The series is arranged as 5 subseries:
  4.1: Books, 1908-1988
  4.2: Exhibition Catalogs, circa 1942-1990
  4.3: Journals, Magazines, and Newspapers, 1948-1989
  4.4: Lectures, 1960-1988
  4.5: Other Writings and Research Notes, 1937-1989, undated
  - Books, 1908-1988; 4.1
    Esther McCoy wrote and published six books on architecture, and contributed writings for several other book projects during her career. This subseries contains records of these writing projects. Files for books written by McCoy may consist of correspondence, draft versions, notes, research material, financial records, photographs, and publicity and reviews. Correspondence may include original correspondence between McCoy and the architects who were the subject of her work; correspondence with publishers and others relating to her work; and copies of correspondence that McCoy used for research. For example, files for her book Vienna To Los Angeles: Two Journeys include copies of correspondence between Richard Neutra and R.M. Schindler and between Frank Lloyd Wright and Aline Barnsdall. Research material and notes document the formation of her ideas and may include notes made during tours of buildings and exhibitions, interview notes, printed material, and excerpts from sources relating to her research, including previous writings about the subjects by McCoy and others.
    This series also contains records of McCoy's work on other book projects, such as writing essays for Contemporary Architects, and writing the introduction for Francisco Artigas. The Artigas material also includes interview transcripts. McCoy's records for Vienna To Los Angeles: Two Journeys includes material for a related article "Letters Between R. M. Schindler and Richard Neutra" and an essay written by Pauline Schindler about Taliesin.
    The bulk of this subseries has been scanned. Photographs by Julius Shulman and Marvin Rand and other select folders have not been scanned.
    Titles of works are arranged alphabetically and individual files are also arranged alphabetically. McCoy's books Five California Architects and The Second Generation featured sections on specific architects, and her correspondence, drafts, and research material are all alphabetically arranged by architect.
    - Photograph of Publications (Books), circa 1970s (Box 14, Folder 28)
    - Collier's Encyclopedia, "Richard Josef Neutra,", 1959, 1985 (Box 14, Folder 29)